Finding Aid to the William Church Osborn Records, 1904-1953 Archives.Osborn.1
The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives
William Church Osborn Records
1904-1953
Archives.Osborn.1
The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives
1.5 Linear feet (5 boxes)
William Church Osborn was a longtime trustee of The Metropolitan Museum of Art who also served as the institution's Vice President, President and Honrary President. Records consist primarily of correspondence regarding all aspects of Museum operations including acquisitions, exhibitions, fundraising, personnel and trustee affairs.
Osborn, Wm. Church, (William Church), 1862-1951
Conditions Governing Access note
Collection is open to research.
Selected files relating to personnel, trustee affairs and confidential Museum business are available to Museum staff only.
Scope and Contents note
Records consist primarily of correspondence to and from William Church Osborn and relate to all aspects of Museum operations including acquisitions, exhibitions, educational programs, facilities, fundraising, relations with New York City, personnel and Trustee matters. Prominent correspondents include Bashford Dean, Roland Redmond, William M. Ivins, Lee Simonson, Herbert E. Winlock, James Rorimer, Robert Woods de Forest, Francis Henry Taylor and Robert Moses. There is substantial documentation regarding the planning and construction of The Cloisters, proposed expansion and renovation of the main Museum building, the search for a Museum Director following the 1931 death of Edward Robinson, the activities of the Museum's Seventy-Fifth Anniversary Committee, cooperation with other New York museums and relations with government agencies (particularly the New York City Parks Department under Robert Moses).
Related Archival Materials note
Office of the Secretary Records, The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives.
Francis Henry Taylor Records, The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives.
Osborn Family Osborn and Dodge Family Papers, 1726-1983, Princeton University.
Other Finding Aids note
An inventory and summary of the records prepared in 1971 by former Museum Archivist John Buchanan is available. Consult Archives staff for further information.
Arrangement note
Two series: 1. Subjects; 2. Chronological Correspondence.
Biographical/Historical note
Lawyer and civic leader William Church Osborn (1862-1951) was a longtime trustee of The Metropolitan Museum of Art. He also served on the boards of a number of charitable and educational institutions, including the Children's Aid Society and his alma mater, Princeton University. Although he never ran for elective office, Osborn was active in the political arena as organizer and president of the Society to Prevent Corrupt Practices at Elections, as chairman of the New York State Democratic Committee, and as founder, president, and chairman of the Citizens Budget Commission. Osborn was first elected a trustee of The Metropolitan Museum of Art in May 1904. He later served as Vice President (1932-1941), President (1941-1947) and Honorary President (1947-1951). Significant events during the period of Osborn’s leadership of the Metropolitan include the celebration of the Museum’s 75th anniversary, the construction of several new building wings, and the appointment of Francis Henry Taylor as the institution’s fifth Director. Osborn made several important gifts of artwork to the Museum, including such paintings as Edouard Manet’s “The Spanish Singer” and Paul Gauguin’s “Two Tahitian Women.” Through his bequest he left to the Metropolitan works by Monet, Pissarro and William Blake.
Bach, Richard F., 1888-1968 -- Correspondence; De Forest, Robert W., (Robert Weeks), 1848-1931 -- Correspondence; Dean, Bashford, 1867-1928 -- Correspondence; Ivins, William Mills, 1881-1961 -- Correspondence; James J. Rorimer, (James Joseph), 1905-1966 -- Correspondence; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.). Board of Trustees.; Moses, Robert, 1888-1981 -- Correspondence; Redmond, Roland Livingston, 1892-1982 -- Correspondence; Saxe, John Godfrey, b. 1877 -- Correspondence; Simonson, Lee, 1888-1967 -- Correspondence; Taylor, Francis Henry, 1903-1957 -- Correspondence; Winlock, Herbert E., 1884-1950 -- Correspondence; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.) -- Administration.; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.) -- Management.; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.) -- Officials and employees.
- Series 1. Subjects
  Scope and Contents note
  Series consists of paper, paper and more paper.
  - Administration, Museum., 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Handicraft Council., 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Craftsmen's Cooperative Council, Inc., 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Craftsmen's Educational Council, Inc., 1949-1953 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Art Objects, expert opinion on., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bache Collection., 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bahr Collection., 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Building., 1908, 1928-1935, 1941-1947 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - By-laws., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clearwater, Alphonso Trumpbour., 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cloisters., 1935-1936, 1942, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 13-18)
  - Committee Reorganization., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Constitution., 1944, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Counsel, Museum., 1942-1944; Regarding fees of De Forest & Elder (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Costume Institute., 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dale, Chester., 1932, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Dean, Bashford., 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Demonstration material., 1920, 1934-1940 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Development Committee., 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 26-35)
  - Development Committee., 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Development Committee - Reports., 1940-1943 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Director, selection of., 1931, 1937, 1939, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Educational Work., 1943-1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Finances., 1929, 1941, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - French, Daniel Chester., 1926 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fundraising., 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 9-15)
  - Gary, Emma T. - Estate., 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Gifts, disposal of., 1928 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Havemeyer, Louisine W., bequest of - Extracts from will., 1929 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - History of the Museum., 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Ivins, William Mills, Jr.., 1939, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - James, Arthur Curtiss - Estate., 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Ludlow, Mrs. Fulton., 1930-1932, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Mayor, A. Hyatt., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Modern American Art., 1927, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Moses, Robert., 1943-1946 (Box 2, Folder 25-27)
  - Museum Estates., 1931, 1941-1945 (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
  - Museum of Modern Art., 1934-1935, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - New York City - Budget., 1934, 1937, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - New York City - Department of Parks., 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - New York University - Institute of Fine Arts., 1943 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - New Yorker article., 1939 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Paintings, Curator of., 1946 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Pieta, Palestrina., 1937 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Pieta, Rondanini., 1945 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Real estate, disposal of., 1929 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Reorganization, Museum., 1926 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Secretary, Museum., 1944 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Security., 1944 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Stokes, Isaac Newton Phelps., 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Verplanck Room., 1939, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Wentworth Collection., 1937 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art., 1942-1943, 1945-1947 (Box 4, Folder 6-11)
  - Winlock, Herbert Eustis., 1937, 1939, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Series 2. Chronological Correspondence
  Other Finding Aids note
  For a summary of the contents of significant letters included in this series refer to the 1971 finding aid by John Buchanan; consult Archives staff for access.
  - 1930-1931, 1934-1939., 1930-1939 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 1941-1942. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - January-March, 1943. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - April-December, 1943. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - January-May, 1944. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - June-December, 1944. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - January-May, 1945. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - June-December, 1945. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - 1946-1947. (Box 4, Folder 21)